בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is פא, pe alef, 81.
We start already. We start on פא עמוד ב, pe amud bet,
yeah.
I'd like this to be for the recovery of Rabbi Zalman Teitelbaum,
שניאור זלמן בן חיה לאה, Shneur Zalman ben Chaya Leah, who was
seriously injured in an auto accident, אוי, oy, last
מוצאי שבת. Motzaei Shabbat. He is a חב״ד Chabad rabbi at the
Albert Einstein College of Medicine. ברוך השם Baruch Hashem he is likely
to recover from his injuries.
Yeah, it should be for רפואה שלמה. refuah sheleimah.
Okay, so we pick up in the middle of פא עמוד ב,
pe amud bet, and it's the two dots of ניתוספו עליהם. nitosfu
alehem. It's almost exactly in the middle of the דף, daf, it's
across from the תוספות אלא. Tosafot ella.
And the line starts with the word אימא. eima. So the two
dots, ניתוספו עליהם מוסיף ומזכה. nitosfu alehem mosif u'mezake. So this is
talking about somebody had collected the food for the עירוב eruv or
the שיתוף, shituf, and then there was a minimum amount, which we're
going to get to, and then that amount got somehow depleted. It
was eaten, rats, who knows what happened.
So if you're coming to replenish and it's of the, the גמרא
Gemara said, of the same type of thing, it had been wine
and you want to add more wine,
then you don't need to ask them. If it's of a different
type of a thing, you wanted to replenish it with let's say
oil, then under certain circumstances if you were doing it all from
scratch again, everything had been used up, you might have to ask
them. What's also not clear is whether you're taking their stuff or
your stuff. Presumably, based on the earlier discussion, if you're using your
stuff and just giving it to them, why do you have to
ask their permission? You're just doing them a benefit. But if you're
using their stuff and you have access to their stuff, then you
might have to ask them. They had already indicated they want to
participate, but if you're doing something significantly new, then you might have
to ask them.
Now, if there are new members of the courtyard between last שבת
Shabbos and this שבת, Shabbos, some people moved in, so the משנה
Mishnah says you add to the food and you צריך להודיע, tzarich
lehodiya, you have to inform them. So again, not exactly clear whether
you are informing them because you are taking from their food or
you're using your food and even when you're using your food you
have to inform them. Again, that's an ambiguous point in the משנה.
Mishnah. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רב שיזבי
אמר רב חסדא זאת אומרת חלוקין עליו חבריו ארבי יהודה. Amar Rav
Shizbi amar Rav Chisda: Zot omeret chalukin alav chaverav al Rabbi Yehuda.
This says that Rabbi Yehuda's colleagues disagree with him. Which Rabbi Yehuda?
דתנן, de-tan, we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, and this is coming
up later today in the next דף: daf: אמר רבי יהודה במה
דברים אמורים, Amar Rabbi Yehuda: Bameh devarim amurim, when is this true
that you need to get somebody's buy-in if you're making an עירוב
eruv for them and have to inform them? בעירובי תחומין, be-eruvei techumin,
when you are making an עירוב תחומין eruv techumin for a person,
because if you make an עירוב תחומין eruv techumin for a person,
you're not always helping him. You're extending the area in one direction
and you're shortening it in the other direction. So there clearly you
need the person's buy-in from the beginning. אבל בעירובי חצירות, aval be-eruvei
chatzerot, when you're doing an עירוב eruv of the yards and you're
basically letting everybody carry in the yard, מערבין בין לדעתו בין שלא
לדעתו, me'arvin ben l'daato ben shelo l'daato, you don't need this person's
awareness, you're only helping the person.
So the גמרא Gemara assumes that our משנה Mishnah that says that
even when you're doing this עירוב eruv for the new members of
the courtyard that you have to inform them, this is clearly in
contradiction, or not contradiction, in conflict with Rabbi Yehuda's position that when
you're doing an עירוב חצירות eruv chatzerot you don't have to inform.
Again, the key question that's missing from this discussion is whose food
are you using? Right? You could say in one case you have
to inform because in our משנה Mishnah because you're using their food.
Maybe in Rabbi Yehuda's case you don't have to inform because you're
using your food. The גמרא Gemara does not see that as a
difference. Okay, the גמרא Gemara is not getting, somehow assumes that that's
the same in both cases. So Rabbi Yehuda says you don't have
to inform and our משנה Mishnah says you do have to inform.
So the גמרא Gemara says: פשיטא דחלוקין, peshita de-chalukin,
obviously they're arguing. Our משנה Mishnah says you do have to inform,
Rabbi Yehuda says you don't. No. מה דתימא, ma d'teima, I might
have thought: הני מילי בחצר שבין שני מבואות, hani mili be-chatzer she-bein
shtei mav'ot, when does our משנה Mishnah say you have to inform?
This is like we discussed yesterday, when you have a courtyard that's
between two alleyways and the courtyard can opt which alley to make
an עירוב eruv with. So it's not clearly always in its benefit
to make with alley A, maybe it wants to be able to
carry in alley B, maybe it has no interest in alley A.
It's also not necessarily making a problem for alley A that you
can somehow force its participation. So maybe we're talking in a special
case where this courtyard has a choice and isn't even necessarily getting
in the way of other courtyards because it can choose which alley
to associate with. That's where you have to get their buy-in. אבל
חצר שבמבוי אחד, aval chatzer she-bemavoi echad, but if it's only the
courtyard is only of one alleyway where A, it's clear that there's
a benefit to being part of this alley, there's no other alley
it can be part of, and B, it's getting in the way
of other courtyards, אימא לא, eima lo, maybe you wouldn't have to
inform, we actually discussed yesterday a possibility you could forcibly demand their
participation. קא משמע לן, kamashma lan, that that is not the פשט
pshat of our... קא משמע לן, kamashma lan, so maybe that would
have been the issue. Meaning when did Rabbi Yehuda say, when did
our משנה Mishnah say you have to inform? Only if it's this
question about two alleyways. But if there's only one... Maybe our משנה
mishna would agree you don't have to inform, קמשמע לן Kama Shma
Lan that our משנה mishna is talking even if there's only the
one alleyway, and even so it says you have to inform. So
basically what we're saying is that our משנה mishna says that even
if you want to get a courtyard's participation in an עירוב, eruv,
and you want to be מזכה, mezake, you want to use food
for this, you have to get their buy-in. Whereas רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda in the coming up משנה mishna says you do not. Thank
you. And the גמרא Gemara is saying, so that's a debate whether
you have to get their buy-in. And we're talking in both cases
in a scenario where this is the only yard that they can,
this is the only alleyway they can make an עירוב eruv in.
So it's not like they have any other choice. It's by not
participating, they're going to make a problem for others. And nevertheless, and
that's why רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you don't need their buy-in.
And nevertheless our משנה mishna says you do need their buy-in. Again,
what the גמרא Gemara is not addressing is whose food are you
using? Because it's very hard to understand if you're using your food
and it's only for a benefit for them and they're getting in
the way of everyone else, why our משנה mishna would assume you
need their buy-in. So it makes sense to think that the גמרא
Gemara is assuming that you're using their food. But again, the גמרא
Gemara is not addressing that. Okay, so that's the issue about that
point, that the משנה mishna says that when you make an עירוב
eruv for new people, you need their buy-in. And we'll see in
a minute that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda will say that that is
not true. Now, כמה שיעורו, Kama Shiuro, going to the end of
the משנה, mishna, what is the minimum amount of the food needed
for an עירוב? eruv? So it says two breads for everyone, two,
excuse me,
שתי סעודות shtei seudot worth if there's a lot of people, then
שתי סעודות shtei seudot for everybody involved, it could be a thousand
people involved, you make an עירוב eruv for a city, ten thousand
people involved, שתי סעודות shtei seudot suffices. But if it's a small
number of people, then each person has to give the size of
a גרוגרת, grogeret, which is a dried fig. Right,
dried fig or dried date. I keep on getting that wrong. Somebody?
No? Dried fig. Thank you. Okay, כמה שיעורו. Kama Shiuro. So the
גמרא Gemara says,
so כמה הוא מרובין, kama hu merubin, what's a lot of people
that you don't go by the size of a dried fig per
person but you go by שתי סעודות shtei seudot worth? So אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel, שמונה עשר בני
אדם, shmonah asar bnei adam,
eighteen people. So the גמרא Gemara says, שמונה עשר ותו לא, shmonah
asar v'tu lo, what, only eighteen? More than that not? So I
mean we say if large, large is obviously even bigger. So okay,
אימא, eima, what it means is משמונה עשר ואילך, mishmonah asar v'eilach,
eighteen and more is large number and שתי סעודות shtei seudot is
for everyone. Now, what's the significance of that? מאי שמונה עשר דנקט,
Mai shmonah asar de'nakat, where is he getting this word eight, number
eighteen out of the air? So אמר רב יצחק בריה דרב יהודה,
Amar Rav Yitzchak brei de'Rav Yehuda, לדידי מפרשא לי מיניה דאבא, Ledidi
mefarsha li minei d'Abba, so he explained to me in the name
of my father, so
because this is רב יצחק Rav Yitzchak the son of רב יהודה
Rav Yehuda and the statement was in the name of רב יהודה,
Rav Yehuda, כל שאילו מחלקו למזון שתי סעודות ביניהם אין מגיע כגרוגרת
לכל אחד ואחד, Kol she'ilu mechalko le'mazon shtei seudot beineihem ein magia
k'grogeret le'chol echad v'echad,
because if you take the amount of שתי סעודות shtei seudot worth
and you divide it into eighteen portions, then each person is already
giving more than a גרוגרת. grogeret. So the idea is it is
the lesser of a גרוגרת grogeret per person or שתי סעודות shtei
seudot for everyone. So if you have seventeen people and each person
gives a גרוגרת, grogeret, the total amount is less than שתי סעודות
shtei seudot worth. And therefore by seventeen each person is only giving
a גרוגרת. grogeret. But as soon as you hit eighteen, שמונה עשר
גרוגרות shmonah asar grogeros is more than שתי סעודות shtei seudot worth.
So as soon as you hit eighteen, you just go by שתי
סעודות shtei seudot for everybody.
Okay, הן הן מרובין. Hen hen merubin. So if you took it
and you divided שתי סעודות shtei seudot and each person would get
less than a גרוגרת grogeret per person, that's a lot of people,
so you go by שתי סעודות, shtei seudot, וסגי במזון שתי סעודות,
v'sagi be'mazon shtei seudot, you go by שתי סעודות. shtei seudot. ואילו,
V'ilo, and if not, if by dividing it amongst the people everybody
has a גרוגרת grogeret or more, that's מועטין הן, muatin hen, then
that's a small number of people and you don't demand שתי סעודות
shtei seudot for the whole, for everyone, you just do a גרוגרת
grogeret per person. ואגב אורחיה קמשמע לן, V'agav orchieh kama shma lan,
and in passing he's letting you know
דשתי סעודות הויין שמונה עשר גרוגרות, d'shtei seudot havyan shmonah asar grogerot,
that the meal of שתי סעודות shtei seudot is the size of
eighteen pressed figs. Now the only thing we have to figure out
is what is the size of a pressed fig. Okay, anyway, that
is the הלכה halacha about שתי סעודות shtei seudot and that's why,
you know, the rabbi can do it with a box of מצות
matzos because you can have ten thousand people, a hundred thousand people
and שתי סעודות shtei seudot for everyone. Okay, and we're going to
add to that right now in the next משנה. mishna. So what
have we said so far? We said that if you're doing it
for people without their, can you do it for people without their
awareness?
The previous משנה mishna sounded like no, you always, you need their
awareness, although as I said, you could say that that's talking about
using their food, which is consistent with what we've been saying. When
you use your food, you don't need their awareness at all. But
at least in some circumstances the previous משנה mishna said you need
their awareness and we've indicated that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda disagrees. And
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you do not.
That's number one. And number two is שתי סעודות shtei seudot for
everyone. Now we're going to talk about what the food actually is.
Let's look at the next משנה. mishna. בכל מערבין ומשתתפין, Bechol me'arvin
u'mishtatfin, you can use anything for your עירוב eruv or your שיתוף
shituf for the streets, חוץ מן המים ומן המלח, chutz min hamayim
u'min hamelach, with the exception of water and salt. דברי רבי אליעזר.
Divrei Rabbi Eliezer.
So meaning anything that's considered real-life food, you know, as opposed to
these which are spice or water, it's a drink, it's not something
that
really... This might remind you of a משנה mishna we had way
earlier about בכל מערבין, bechol me'arvin, which was talking about עירובי תחומין.
eruvei techumin. This is talking about עירובי חצרות. eruvei chatzeirot. רבי יהושע
אומר כיכר הוא עירוב. Rabbi Yehoshua omer kikar hu eruv. No, you
have to use a loaf of bread.
Now you would have thought it means bread as opposed to other
foodstuffs, but he says even more, it's specifically the loaf of bread,
אפילו מאפה סאה, afilu maafeh se'ah, even if you have the baking
of a סאה se'ah of flour, which is like, you know, a
huge, I don't know, it's like, you know, think like you've got
like a wedding loaf of bread, והוא פרוסה, vehu prusa, but it's
not whole, אין מערבין בה, ein me'arvin bah, you cannot use it.
כיכר כאיסר, Kikar ke'issar, on the other hand, if you have a
tiny little roll that is the size of like a nickel, a
tiny little, a tiny little size, והוא שלם, vehu shalem, as long
as it's whole, מערבין בה, me'arvin bah, you can use it. So,
so use it for whom? So רש״י Rashi says this means, and
I'll talk about the הלכה halacha in a minute, that each individual
has to contribute a whole loaf. It's not whole loaves for everybody
combined. Each individual. So if you took a look at the little
רש״י Rashi at the last רש״י Rashi on the bottom, והוא שלם
מערבין בה ובלבד שיש שם כיכרות הרבה כגרוגרת לכל אחד ואחד. vehu
shalem me'arvin bah uvilvad sheyesh sham kikarot harbeh kegrogeret lechol echad ve'echad.
This is not going against the previous point that everybody has to
contribute the size of a, of a pressed fig, that, you know,
the volume, but everybody has to contribute in the form of a
whole loaf. So if you have a thousand people, you can get,
you have a thousand tiny little loaves. Presumably, what about the הלכה
halacha that you could do מזון שתי סעודות? mazon shtei seudot? So
it's not exactly clear how רש״י Rashi would interpret that. One reasonable
explanation, and we'll get to this in a minute, is if you
have more than eighteen or more people, then you just get two
big loaves or one big loaf, it's not צאי לחם, tzai lechem,
one big loaf and that's for everyone. But when people are contributing
individually, everybody has to contribute a whole loaf. Okay, so this is
not just the idea of bread, but the idea of a whole
loaf and we'll see what that's about in the
גמרא. Gemara. No, it cannot be money. It has to actually be
food according to this. Now if you're taking your food and you're
being transferred the ownership to people, then effectively they've given food, because
then it becomes their food.
Yeah, so we're actually going to see in the משנה mishna coming
up about that, about giving money to somebody to buy for you.
And if in the end the people own the food, that's fine,
however, however that process works. So let's look at the גמרא Gemara
top of פ׳ א׳, Pei Aleph, תנינא חדא זימנא. Tanina chada zimna.
We already taught this idea that you can use any types of
foods. We in the beginning of the פרק perek called בכל מערבין.
Bechol me'arvin. So it says, which was talking about עירובי תחומין, eruvei
techumin, which was a good while ago, you might remember it about
a good two months ago. בכל מערבין ומשתתפין, Bechol me'arvin umishtatfin, you
can use anything for עירוב eruv and שיתוף, shituf, חוץ מן המים
ומן המלח, chutz min hamayim umin hamelach, except for water and salt.
So what's why are we saying it again? So אמר רבה לאפוקי
מדרבי יהושע דאמר כיכר אין מידי אחריני לא. Amar Rabba la'apukei mi-deRabbi
Yehoshua d'amar kikar in midei achrinei lo. Because we hear רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua here says you have to only a loaf of bread,
not other things. So it's saying it twice to tell me that
we're not ruling like it. קא משמע לן בכל. Ka mashma lan
bechol. So it's telling you everything. Now what do you mean, why
did it have to say that? I mean you've already says that
you have a תנא קמא Tanna Kamma saying everything.
Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, so the way רש״י Rashi explains what
the גמרא Gemara says is that you might have thought since רבי
יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua only voices his idea here about bread in this
context of עירובי חצרות, eruvei chatzeirot, you might have thought that he
actually says his position by עירוב תחומין eruv techumin he doesn't demand
bread. So by saying it twice, saying essentially the same משנה mishna
twice, somehow that implies, again it's not clear why it implies, but
somehow it implies that רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that demands bread would
actually held his position in both cases. And therefore we or the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma has to reiterate in both places a position
against רבי יהושע. Rabbi Yehoshua. All right, so that's the way רש״י
Rashi explains it, תוספות Tosafot has a slightly different explanation.
Should he just say or try to say that the הלכה halacha
is not like him? Shouldn't he just say something like the חכמים?
Chachamim? No, it's not saying the הלכה halacha is not like him.
It's saying we want to underscore that the חכמים Chachamim disagree with
him in both places. Okay, so it says like this, instead
of once, but more explicitly?
I, that's a good question. Okay, anyway let's see what the גמרא
Gemara says. איתיביה אביי, Eitveih Abaye, Abaye asked them, we have a
ברייתא. braita. בכל מערבין עירובי חצרות ובכל משתתפין שיתופי מבואות. Bechol me'arvin
eruvei chatzeirot uvechol mishtatfin shitufei mevo'ot. You can use anything for עירובי
חצרות eruvei chatzeirot or שיתוף מבואות. shituf mevo'ot. ולא אמרו לערב בפת
אלא בחצר בלבד. Velo amru le'arev bepat ela bechatzer bilvad. So the
only time you have to use bread is in the courtyard, is
in the courtyard. Now that what do you mean? First you say
you do everything and then you say you need to use bread.
So which is it? So what's what would you say is the
answer to that? Is it obvious how you would solve that problem?
בכל מערבין, Bechol me'arvin, you can use anything for an עירוב, eruv,
right? So, oh
actually, actually no, it's not clear what the answer is because of
the גרסא girsa we have. תוספות׳ס Tosafot's גרסא girsa does not have
the word עירובי חצרות. eruvei chatzeirot. תוספות׳ס Tosafot's גרסא girsa has the
word בכל מערבין ובכל משתתפין ולא אמרו לערב בפת אלא בחצר בלבד.
Bechol me'arvin uvechol mishtatfin velo amru le'arev bepat ela bechatzer bilvad. And
that the reasonable read therefore would be: you can use anything for
an עירוב תחומין eruv techumin and anything for a שיתוף מבואות, shituf
mevo'ot, but when it comes to עירובי חצרות, eruvei chatzeirot, that's when
you need bread. That's the
way... So let's take a look. So מאן שמעת ליה דאמר פת
אין מידי אחריני לא, man shamas leh d'amar pas in midi achrinei
lo, who is the one here that says only bread, right? רבי
יהושע. Rebbi Yehoshua. It's רבי יהושע. Rebbi Yehoshua. דתניא בכל, d'tanya bechol,
and I'm going to read this now תוספות Tosafos's way. The first
half of the ברייתא braisa says you can use anything for עירוב.
eiruv. So how could you first say you can use anything for
עירוב eiruv and then at the end say but you can only
use bread for עירוב חצרות? eiruv chatzeros? So if the answer is
you could use anything for עירוב תחומין, eiruv tchumin, okay, but for
עירוב חצרות eiruv chatzeros you need bread. So תוספות Tosafos you see
that רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua actually agrees by עירוב תחומין. eiruv tchumin.
He doesn't disagree by עירוב תחומין. eiruv tchumin. Okay, is that clear?
Meaning if the ברייתא braisa says in the beginning not the word
עירובי חצרות, eiruvi chatzeros, just says בכל מערבין, bechol me'arvin, you can
use anything for עירוב eiruv or for שיתוף, shituf, but for עירוב
חצרות eiruv chatzeros you need bread. So who says עירוב חצרות eiruv
chatzeros you need bread? רבי יהושע. Rebbi Yehoshua. So what you can
use anything for עירוב eiruv means, when it comes to עירוב תחומין
eiruv tchumin you can use anything. So you see that רבי יהושע
Rebbi Yehoshua agrees by עירוב תחומין. eiruv tchumin. That's the way תוספות
Tosafos understands it. So let's take a look.
One minute.
So it says like this, it says, where, בכל משתתפין ובכל מערבין,
bechol mishtatpin uvechol me'arvin, רבי יהושע, Rebbi Yehoshua, פת אין מידי אחריני
לא, pas in midi achrinei lo, רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua וקתני בכל.
vekatani bechol. אלא אמר רבה בר בר חנה לאפוקי מדרבי יהושע דאמר
שלמה אין פרוסה לא קא משמע לן בכל. ela amar Rabbah bar
bar Chana la'fukei miderbi Yehoshua d'amar shleima in prusa lo kamashmalan bechol.
Okay.
So therefore you're right. What it's really coming to do is again
I'm sort of let me just double check here the תוספות Tosafos
because the way he's reading this because I think he has a
different
גרסא. girsa. One minute.
Right, so what the גמרא Gemara is saying, so the way תוספות
Tosafos reads the answer is that the answer is you're right. They
don't debate the point
of whether you need פת pas by עירובי תחומין. eiruvi tchumin. By
עירוב תחומין eiruv tchumin רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua would agree you don't
need פת. pas. So if that's true why do you have to
repeat it two times? To tell you that when the תנא קמא
Tanna Kamma here says בכל מערבין ומשתתפין, bechol me'arvin umishtatpin,
it's saying that not only are we that we I'm sorry I
said it wrong again, one second.
Right, I'm sorry. So that we are not let me minute, oh
yes, yes, okay, I got it, I got it.
Right, so what the גמרא Gemara tries to say was that what
we're trying to do is say that the ברייתא braisa that says
בכל מערבין, bechol me'arvin, right, here's the question. The משנה Mishnah earlier
that said בכל מערבין bechol me'arvin by עירובי תחומין, eiruvi tchumin, okay,
is that the חכמים Chachamim and do they disagree with רבי יהושע,
Rebbi Yehoshua, right, or does רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua agree in the
case about עירוב תחומין, eiruv tchumin, which was the earlier משנה? Mishnah?
So the גמרא Gemara first tried to say רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua
disagrees. Now and that position was only the חכמים. Chachamim. Now the
גמרא Gemara is saying that actually רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua agrees, okay,
and that position actually was דברי הכל. divrei hakol. So therefore in
this context what does so if that's true that was the בכל
מערבין bechol me'arvin over there that that was דברי הכל. divrei hakol.
So what's the בכל מערבין bechol me'arvin over here mean? It's the
same language.
So what, the form, cut versus whole?
Right, well that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. Meaning
if it's essentially דברי הכל divrei hakol there and here too, there's
not really a debate so much, right? There everybody agrees עירוב תחומין
eiruv tchumin you can use everything. So here what does the בכל
מערבין bechol me'arvin mean? So the גמרא Gemara actually says that בכל
מערבין bechol me'arvin here does not mean you can use everything. Here
the בכל מערבין bechol me'arvin means as Michael says, it is the
form that it is taking. So let's take a look. So לאפוקי
מדרבי יהושע דאמר שלמה
אין פרוסה לא קא משמע לן בכל. la'fukei miderbi Yehoshua d'amar shleima
in prusa lo kamashmalan bechol. You're right. The point about saying it
here is not to say all types of food. Over there when
it was talking about עירוב תחומין, eiruv tchumin, it meant all types
of food and everybody agreed. Here presumably we're shifting and everybody also
fundamentally agrees that it's only bread. So if there everybody agrees all
types of food and here everybody agrees that it's only bread, then
what's the debate? The debate is whether you can use all forms
of bread. So and that's the debate. So לאפוקי מדרבי יהושע דאמר
שלמה אין פרוסה לא קא משמע לן בכל. la'fukei miderbi Yehoshua d'amar
shleima in prusa lo kamashmalan bechol. So any form of the bread,
it doesn't have to be שלמה, shleima, it could be שלמה shleima
or broken. All right, so that's the way the גמרא Gemara now
is concluding that when it comes to עירוב תחומין eiruv tchumin it
can be everything and maybe even רבי יהושע Rebbi Yehoshua agrees. When
it comes to עירובי חצרות, eiruvi chatzeros, then it's possible to read
it that even the חכמים Chachamim say although again it doesn't sound
like it because it says
חכמים. Chachamim. is that
debate
about? So ופרוסה מאי טעמא לא, u-frusa mai ta'ama lo, why can
it not be a portion of a loaf according to רבי יהושע?
Rabbi Yehoshua? So אמר רבי יוסי בן שאול אמר רבי משום איבה
amar Rabbi Yosi ben Shaul amar Rabbi mishum eivah because of enmity.
Now what's the enmity? So רש"י Rashi says the enmity is is
that it's sort of like you know the idea when everybody all
the women would wear white, you want to do something that's like
a stand right on the you know ט"ו בשבט, Tu BiShvat, so
you want to do something that's like a ט"ו באב Tu B'Av
excuse me, you want to do something that's a standard so that
it's not like oh I gave a whole loaf, you gave a
tiny little half of a loaf. So if everybody is giving a
half a loaf, therefore a whole loaf, therefore it gets rid of
this competition.
Let everybody just give a half a loaf.
Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. Okay, so
אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי עירבו כולם בפרוסות מאי,
amar lei Rav Acha brei de-Rava le-Rav Ashi eirvu kulam be-frusot mai,
let's say everybody gave a portion of a loaf? So אמר ליה
שמא יחזור דבר לקלקולו. amar lei shema yachzor davar le-kilkulo. No, because
then we're afraid that once you start allowing a half a loaf,
somebody's going to say hey I can afford a whole loaf and
they'll give a whole loaf. So therefore again it doesn't make sense
to require people to give a half a loaf. So therefore we're
going to require everyone... Then they'll give a bigger loaf. I understand,
I understand. Now if you actually say what happens is that once
you have more than a certain number of people you use שתי
סעודות shtei se'udot worth and you do it for everyone, then you
actually also see a nice idea here which is not clear it
doesn't sound not necessarily what the גמרא Gemara means but it's a
nice idea of this איבה eivah idea. It's like all these small
you know all the individuals coming together for a larger whole. So
the idea that not necessarily what each person contributes is a whole,
but that the totality is a whole and I'll read you a
רמ"א Rema a minute about what our practice is. You understand because
look the whole idea about עירוב Eruv itself like the גמרא Gemara
wants you know said before עירוב שמו, Eruv shemo, the whole idea
is creating a sense of community and coming together and a coherent
sort of you know group. So the idea that that expresses itself
by a whole loaf a sense of a you know smaller things
coming together for something larger, which is essentially what you make bread
right you take flour whatever, you bring it together, there's something very
symbolic about that. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't sound... Right. Right. But
the גמרא Gemara yeah but the גמרא Gemara is talking here about
what you're... to sounds like you're talking about what you're contributing, not
just what you end up with. Okay, so אמר רבי יוחנן בן
שאול ניטלה הימנה כדי חלה וכדי דימוע מערבין בה. amar Rabbi Yochanan
ben Shaul nitla heimena k'dei challah u-k'dei dimua me'arvin bah. How big
is whole or not? Like you can imagine these questions also by
שתי הלחם shtei halechem by שבת. Shabbat. Let's say the from the
loaf of bread was taken חלה, challah, right? You take a you
know when you're making a certain quantity of bread you have to
take חלה challah or let's say some תרומה terumah fell in or
the חלה challah fell back into the loaf, so then even when
it's בטל batel there's like a hundred times of it and it's
בטל, batel, you have to take one one-hundredth. You have to remove
one one-hundredth and that's called דימוע. dimua. If there became this mixture
that the תרומה terumah or חלה challah fell into the loaf. So
let's say you removed that from the loaf presumably after it was
already baked. Is that still considered whole or not if it's missing
a little bit? So so what's the story? מערבין בה. me'arvin bah.
So he says you can use it for the עירוב. Eruv. והתניא
כדי דימוע מערבין בה כדי חלה אין מערבין בה? ve-hatanya k'dei dimua
me'arvin bah k'dei challah ein me'arvin bah? Wait a minute, we say
if it's the דימוע dimua amount because דימוע dimua is only one
one-hundredth, it's a very tiny amount, then you can still use it
for the עירוב. Eruv. If it's the חלה challah amount, which is
one-twenty-fourth or one-forty-eighth, you cannot. So how could you say in both
cases you can? So לא קשיא הא בחלת נחתום הא בחלת בעל
הבית. lo kashya ha be-challas nactom ha be-challas ba'al habayit.
It depends whether it's a homeowner's bread or a baker's bread because
that determines the percentage of how much you take for חלה. challah.
דתנן, de-tnan, we saw in the משנה, Mishnah, שיעור חלה אחד מעשרים
וארבעה. shiur challah echad me-esrim ve-arba'ah. חלה challah is one-twenty-fourth of the
of what you're baking. העושה עיסה לעצמו, ha-oseh isah le-atzmo, now if
you're making it for your own if for your own consumption, והעושה
למשתה בנו ve-ha-oseh le-mishteh beno and even if you're making like a
hundred loaves of bread for your son's wedding, a thousand loaves of
bread, but you're still as a private individual doing it, so it's
not about quantity, it's about you as a private individual doing it,
אחד מעשרים וארבעה, echad me-esrim ve-arba'ah, you take one-twenty-fourth. נחתום, nactom, now
if you're a baker, שהוא עושה למכור בשוק, she-hu oseh limkor ba-shuk,
if you're doing it to sell in the marketplace, וכן האשה שעשתה
למכור בשוק ve-chein ha-ishah she-astah limkor ba-shuk or even somebody that sells
home-baked bread out of their home but you're doing it for sale
purposes not for private consumption so it's not quantity it's what purpose
you're doing it for you're doing it to make money you're doing
it to sell, in those cases אחד מארבעים ושמונה, echad me-arba'im u-shmonah,
one-forty-eighth which you can understand either is a way of saying we
don't want to give a you know we're doing it says a
rough estimate of quantity but what it makes more sense to say
is is that if you're doing it to make money we want
to have a little רחמנות rachmanus on you and help you make
a little bit more of a you know of a profit margin
and we're not going to demand as much. Okay, but either way
what it says is is that when you take one-twenty-fourth, which is
a larger amount, then the loaf is no longer considered whole and
you can't use it for the עירוב Eruv according to רבי יהושע.
Rabbi Yehoshua. When you take one-forty-eighth, which is a smaller amount, like
a two percent, then it's not so lacking and then it would
be it would still be considered שלם. shalem. Again this question comes
up all the time, you know, you when you break your loaves
of bread and there's like this little cut you know little... place
where it's separate, is that really whole yet or not? A little
chip of the מצה *matzah*'s off. When is it considered separate? Now
תוספות Tosafot, *Tosfos* points out the use of the word כדי *k'dei*,
כדי חלתה *k'dei chalasah*, כדי דמוע *k'dei dimua*. Why doesn't it say
ניטל חלתה *nital chalasah*, the חלה challah. *challah* was taken? So תוספות
Tosafot *Tosfos* says maybe what it means is that you didn't even
take חלה *challah*, but the quantity that's lacking, a piece broke off,
but it's equivalent to the amount of חלה *challah*, meaning it's one
twenty-fourth, or one forty-eighth, or one one-hundredth. So it's just a way
of defining how much broke off. It's not actually saying you've removed
חלה *challah*. So תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* in the end doesn't like that
interpretation. He says only when you really took חלה *challah* are we
going to say it's not lacking. But if a piece broke off
just סתם stam *stam*, it would always be a problem. But he
admits, he acknowledges that a reasonable reader of the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
is that even if it broke off by accident, not related to
חלה *challah* or תרומה *terumah*, if it's a small amount, the size
of those types of things, that might not be a problem.
Before even things like דבר מצווה mitzvah. *davar mitzvah* you have to
take חלה *challah*.
Well, you're supposed to take חלה מן העיסה *challah min ha'issa* anyway.
But yes. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: so once
they actually make the loaf lacking. אמר רב Amar Rav חסדא *Amar
Rav Chisda*. Now, again, what you will notice is the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* has moved into a shift of assuming רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua
*Rabbi Yehoshua*. We're now just talking about what defines whole, almost taking
for granted the position of רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua*, which is also
a little bit consistent with it seems that the way the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* read the משנה mishnah. *Mishnah*, one way it read the
משנה mishnah: *Mishnah* is that even the חכמים chachamim *chachamim* don't agree
with רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua* about the use of bread, the only
question is whole, and now the גמרא gemara *Gemara* is focusing on
this discussion of whether what constitutes whole. That's what I'm trying to
understand.
Is that what we're saying, that really everyone agrees with רבי יהושע
*Rabbi Yehoshua*? That's our final... about bread?
According to... that's certainly what the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* seems to be
saying. It was an unclear גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, like I said, רש"י
Rashi, *Rashi* and תוספות Tosfos *Tosfos* had different reads about it, but
yes, it seems like that is what it's saying. But my point
is, more than that, the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* now seems to be
assuming רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua*. Let's take a look. אמר רב חסדא
*Amar Rav Chisda*, תפרו בקיסם מערבין בו *tafra bekisam mearvin bo*. You
have your loaf of bread, it broke in half. You take a
little toothpick and you hold the two halves together. So he says
you sewed it, literally sewed it with a stick, with a like
a little splinter, then that's okay. So the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*... so
that's considered whole. והתניא אין מערבין בו *ve'ha tanya ein mearvin bo*,
you can't use it. לא קשיא *lo kashya*. הא דידיע תפרא הא
דלא ידיע תפרא *ha d'yedia tafra ha d'lo yedia tafra*. It depends
how obvious it is that it's being held together, right? You can
do it in a more invisible way if you do it on
the inside than on the outside. So anyway, if it looks whole
and it's being held together, that's okay. Again, notice the assumption that
we have to להלכה le'halacha? *l'halacha* figure out what's whole, the assumption
we're ruling like רבי יהושע *Rabbi Yehoshua*. אמר רב זירא אמר שמואל
Amar Shmuel מערבין בפת אורז *Amar Rav Zeira Amar Shmuel mearvin bepas
orez*. Now we get also to another possible meaning of the word
בכל *bakol*, not just בכל *bakol* in the sense of what form
it's in, but also in the question about what ingredients you used
for the bread. Okay, so he says you can make... use bread,
rice bread, even though it's not normally bread להלכה *l'halacha*. ובפת דוחן
*ubepas dochen*, or spelt bread. אמר מר עוקבא *Amar Mar Ukva*, ובדידי
מפרשא לי מיניה דמר שמואל Shmuel *u-vididi mefarsha li minei d'mar Shmuel*,
to me it was explained in the name of שמואל *Shmuel*, פת
pat. אורז מערבין פת דוחן אין מערבין *pas orez mearvin pas dochen
ein mearvin*. You can use rice bread, but you cannot use millet
bread, which is apparently less
edible. דוחן *dochen* is lentil.
I'm sorry, lentil.
Don't you make המוציא *hamotzi* on... no, not spelt.
Wait, as a celiac, I know rice.
Yeah, how do they translate דוחן *dochen*? I mistranslated it. How do
they translate it? Millet.
Millet. אורז *orez* is rice and that never counts.
Right, I know, so that's the point. It's not about המוציא *hamotzi*
here. It's not about המוציא *hamotzi*.
Why does it have to be כיכר *kikar*?
Why not an apple? Well, again, there's this symbol... you mean because
it looks like... well, okay, why כיכר *kikar*? Right, the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* said שלם *shalem* because of the idea of like איבה *eiva*.
In terms of the issue of why כיכר *kikar*, presumably because it's
more satiating. I mean, you still make מזונות *mezonos* on rice. Right,
so it's still seen as a staple. It's not להלכה *halachically* bread.
That's the חידוש *chiddush* here. I agree, I agree. So, yeah, I
should not have said spelt because that's normally interpreted as one of
the חמשת מינים *chamishas minim*. It says there millet. I have no
idea what millet is. What is millet?
We'll have to find out.
Okay, fine, millet. So he makes a difference between rice and millet.
So, and yes, and that's exactly the חידוש *chiddush*, even though normally
it is not bread and
you don't
make המוציא *hamotzi*.
Is there a reason why? Well, we're going to see. It has
to do with how reasonably edible it is. But I do assume
that even by saying rice bread, the point still is that even
if להלכה *halachically* it's not לחם *lechem*, it still is because a
staple and satiating, and therefore it is that's what qualifies here. אמר
רבי חייא בר אבין אמר רב מערבין בפת עדשים *Amar Rabbi Chiya
bar Abin Amar Rav mearvin bepas adashin*. You can use even one
made out of lentil beans. I guess you grind them up and
make flour out of the beans. איני *ini*? והא האי דהוה בשני
דמר שמואל *ve'ha hi de'hava bi'shnei d'mar Shmuel*... Is that true? Wasn't
there some person in the time of שמואל *Shmuel*, ושדייה לכלביה *ve'shadi
lekhalbei*, he made a lentil bean bread and he threw it to
his dog to see how edible it was, ולא אכליה *velo achlei*,
and even the dog wouldn't eat it! So the גמרא *Gemara* says...
right, it's like the toothpaste test. The גמרא *Gemara* says ההיא דשאר
מינים הוה *hahi de'shari minim hava*. No, that wasn't just lentils. That
was a multi-grain bread. דכתיב ואתה קח לך חטין ושעורין *de'ketiv ve'atah
kach lekha chitin u-se'orim*... this is God speaking to יחזקאל Yechezkel, *Yechezkel*:
take to you wheat and barley... wheat and barley, ופול ועדשים and
those different types of lentils, ודוחן vedochon which is millet, וכסמין vechusmin
how do they translate that? Spelt. That's spelt. Okay. Et cetera so
all that type of thing is not really fit for eating for
people. But a normal, a normal one made out of just simply
one made out of beans, that would be reasonably edible. So what
can I tell you?
Yeah, that's now an expensive bread in health food stores.
I know, I'm going to talk about them in a minute. Quiet.
רב פפא אמר ההיא צלויה בצואת אדם הוה. Rav Pappa amar hahi
tzluya betzo'at adam hava. That presumably, both that that was made by
this guy to his dog and that that was God told to
יחזקאל, Yechezkel? was baked by, you know, by burning human excrement for
the fire. If you look at תוספות, Tosfos תוספות Tosfos says: what's
this guy doing? תוספות Tosfos says וההיא דהוה בשני דמר שמואל אתו
לנסות מה טעמא לפי שציווה הקדוש ברוך הוא ליחזקאל לעשות. ve'hahi de'hava
bishnei de'mar Shmuel atu lenasot mah ta'ama lefi she'tziva HaKadosh Baruch Hu
le'Yechezkel la'asot.
He wanted to do an experiment: what is this bread that God
had commanded יחזקאל? Yechezkel So he made it and he saw that
it was really inedible, and that's part of the whole story that
יחזקאל Yechezkel, is supposed to eat this bread that's inedible and so
on. So the גמרא says what made it inedible, apparently for this
guy and for יחזקאל, Yechezkel was not just that it was multi-grain
but that it used human excrement to burn to bake the bread.
Where were we? דכתיב והיא בגללי צואת אדם תעגנה Dichtiv ve'hi begilalei
tzo'at adam te'agennah and you should bake it with the, you know,
with the human excrement. So לעיניהם le'eineihem to their eyes. מאי עוגת
שעורים תאכלנה? Mai ugat se'orim tochalennah? Why does it say by the
פסוק pasuk also you should eat these cakes of barley? It wasn't
just barley. So אמר רב חסדא לשיעורים. amar Rav Chisda lishiurim. So
another thing God was telling him is eat it little by little.
To also to sort of symbolize, you know, the sense about how
inedible it was and the sense that also it was a time
of, if you look at רש"י, Rashi. דרך—no, derech I'm sorry, not
רש"י. Rashi
Anyway, the point was to show you like that sense about being
in a time of starvation and being and privation and so on.
So and that you would eat things even made out of this
and you would eat it little by little. רב פפא אמר עריבותא
כעריבת שעורים ולא כעריבת חטים. Rav Pappa amar arivuta ke'arivat se'orim velo
ke'arivat chitin. The way you would actually like, you know, the kneading
trough, the way you would actually even process it and knead it
when you're making it, is you do it the way you do
barley and not the way you do wheat, which presumably is a,
you know, is a not as nice way of making it, it
doesn't turn out as nice of a product. So in result of
that, I wanted to show you two things. First of all, people
might have realized as I'm reading this about this multi-grain bread based
on the פסוק pasuk in יחזקאל that there's this product out there
called Ezekiel 4:9 bread. Which has
which it says as described in the Holy Scriptures: take unto wheat
and barley and beans and lentils and millet and spelt, there you
go, millet and spelt, and put them in a vessel and make
bread out of it. Okay. The only problem being that as the
גמרא says, you're supposed to use it was supposed, the whole point
was that it wasn't edible and that it was a curse. So
I found this thing on the web, like anything on the web,
where this guy basically makes this whole point about here he says
first of all he says I tasted the bread it tasted awful.
Anyway then he says, he says the problem here is the biblical
recipe was intended to help survive famine during an upcoming siege, not
because it tastes good or is healthy for you. Barley and millet
throughout history has been considered poor man's food. It's used to feed
livestock, millet is bland tasting grass mainly for disadvantaged countries to feed
the poor, et cetera, et cetera. So then, and then he gets
to the point of I, you know, I have no idea why
they said Ezekiel 4:9 bread, they should have gone to 4:12 where
you actually make it with dung. So and then he has a
little fun poking fun at that. He actually quotes an interesting thing,
so here if you want to sort of see the pictures of
the bread. He has a little, he actually points out that some
scholars say that they didn't actually use the human dung for fuel
because that would have made the most god-awful smell and it would
not have been the greatest fuel, they actually used the human dung
as an ingredient to retain the water when they're cooking it. So
that is even, you know, whatever, more disgusting, but some people think
that that's פשט pshat of what's going on there. Now in terms
of הלכה, halacha, so we have this idea that the גמרא seems
to be focusing on the position of רבי יהושע that you need
whole loaves of bread. So and רש"י Rashi said it meant everybody
gives a little bit. So what do you do להלכה? So here
in the שולחן ערוך, Shulchan Aruch, the שולחן ערוך Shulchan Aruch says
שס"ו ו shin samech vav vav אין מערבין בפרוסה אפילו גדולה הרבה
אבל בשלמה אפילו קטנה מאוד מערבין ובלבד שיהא בכולה שיעור ein me'arvin
be'perusah afilu gedolah harbeh aval bishlemah afilu ketanah me'od me'arvin uvilvad sheyehei
bekulah shiur okay, ומיהו ניטל umihu nital et cetera, et cetera, and
then he speaks about if a little bit is taken for חלה.
So he just says straight you need whole loaves. The רמ"א Rema
says ויש שפירשו הא דאין מערבין רק בפת שלם היינו שכל העירוב
ביחד יהיה פת שלם. ve'yesh she'perishu ha de'ein me'arvin rak bepat shalem
hainu shekol ha'eiruv beyachad yihiye pat shalem. It doesn't mean everybody has
to contribute a פת שלם, pat shalem, it means that the end
product is a whole פת. וכן נהגו לקבץ מכל בית ובית מעט
קמח. vechein nahagu lekabetz mikol bayit uvayit me'at kemach. Everybody gives a
little flour. So this is very beautiful, I want to read this
to you because of that sense of sort of coming together and
community and ending in a sense of a wholeness and a unified,
how this became translated in practice. Everybody gives a little flour ועושין
חלה אחת שלימה ומערבין בה ve'osin challah achas sheleima u'mearvin bah and
it was everybody's flour, you make one loaf of bread, and that
becomes the עירוב, eiruv, and that's very symbolic. Okay, וכן המנהג פשוט
בכל מדינות אלו vechein haminhag pashut bechol medinos eilu and you have
to make sure that this loaf is big enough that it has
two סעודות seudos worth. And then he says,
and then the משנה ברורה, Mishnah Berurah, okay, so that's number one
that it gets translated as not everybody gives one, but it's interesting
מתני' איבא, matni eiva, it gets translated in a way in which
it really is about everybody coming together for one greater whole with
the פסק, psak, and that's why I say you just take a
box of matzos. First of all the matzos last, it doesn't go
bad, it's whole loaves. So you take the box of matzos and
you're מזכה mezakeh it's two סעודות seudos worth, you קונה koneh it
for the whole community and you're done. Now I did want to
read to you that the משנה ברורה Mishnah Berurah gets into the
whole discussion which is going to be the continued discussion which we've
been talking about and continues to talk about, the idea of transferring
ownership to everyone, and he just brings down this practice about how
we do it nowadays. I just want to read to you for
a second. He says like this, he says
וכן נוהגים שהשמש נותן העירוב להרב בערב פסח שיזכה בו בשביל כל
הקהל. vechein nohagim shehashamash nosein haeiruv leharav be'erev pesach sheyizakeh bo bishvil
kol hakahal. Okay, so they did this every ערב פסח. erev pesach.
Again, I assume that they were also using matzos there as well,
so obviously you're not going to do it with anything other than
matzos ערב פסח. erev pesach.
And then you have to, it's not enough and you have actually
to take possession for everyone as we've been learning. ואם חשכה לו
יום טוב ראשון ולא זיכה, ve'im chashechah lo yom tov rishon velo
zichah, then he discusses what happens if you forgot to actually take
the possession for everyone, how, whether, you know, under what circumstances you
have to transfer ownership or not, staying into our the גמרא as
we've been talking about. But I just want you to see that
that really is the פשט pshat of how we do it. A
box of matzos, two סעודות seudos worth, whole bread, transfer ownership, take
possession from a different party in order to take possession for everybody
and that's what makes what we do it now for everybody. No?
Right. That's the way we do it. Right, cuts short, you know.
We're very, we just, we'd rather throw money at things than actually
bake our own bread. So it's easier to go to the store
and just buy a box of matzos. But in the רמ"א's Rema's
description it's very beautiful that everybody gives a little flour. Okay, let's
take a look now at the next משנה. Mishna, נותן אדם מעה
לחנווני. nosein adam ma'ah lechanvani. So here you go Joe, talking about
having somebody buy it for you. You can if you give a,
you know, your a מעה, ma'ah, certain amount of money, a dollar
to
the shopkeeper, ולנחתום כדי שיזכה לו עירוב דברי רבי אליעזר. velanachtom kedei
sheyizkeh lo eiruv divrei Rabbi Eliezer. You give it to the storekeeper
or to the baker and you say, when the bread is baked,
you know, or for, you know, when somebody comes to collect bread
for the עירוב, eiruv, then a portion of that should be mine
and here's a dollar. That's good, that's what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
says. וחכמים אומרים לא זכו לו מעותיו. vachachamim omrim lo zachu lo
ma'osav. It didn't work. Why? Because מעות, ma'os, money, isn't קונה. koneh.
When you want to buy things that are movable items, you have
to do הגבהה hagbahah or משיכה. meshichah. Money does not do it.
So therefore you never actually took possession of the, of the loaf
of bread. You only paid money for it. Now what about the
fact that the person coming for the community takes the loaf of
bread and takes possession of it for the whole community? Right? So
that includes you. So actually you got yourself in a, in a
situation here because by giving the money you indicated that you wanted
your portion of bread to be the stuff that you were purchasing,
not the portion that was being given to you freely by this
fact that it was taken possession for the whole community. So therefore
the חכמים say you're sort of, you know, נישט אהין נישט אהער.
nisht ahin nisht aher. The buying it didn't work and by buying
it you ruled yourself out of those that were receiving it freely
by the, by the community, by you know one person takes possession
for the whole group. ומודים בשאר כל אדם שזיכו לו מעותיו. umodim
bish'ar kol adam shezichu lo ma'osav. But they agree that with another
person the money would work. What does that mean another person the
money would work? You don't go to the baker or to the,
or to the storekeeper. You go to your friend, Joe this is
your case, and I go over to Charlie and I say, Charlie,
here's a buck, you know, go make the עירוב, eiruv, you know,
make me a partner in the עירוב. eiruv. So I'm not buying
bread from Charlie, I'm asking Charlie to be be a שליח shaliach
and making him an agent. And when Charlie will therefore go take
the bread, he'll take possession of it for me as well. Okay,
so when you're not purchasing you're just, you know, paying somebody to
do it for you then that person actually will take possession of
the bread for
you. Okay. So let's take a look. שאין מערבין לאדם אלא מדעתו.
she'ein mearvin leadam ela mida'ato. Now why does it not work if
I paid the baker? I mean at the end of the day,
you know, they're going to use that bread for the עירוב. eiruv.
No, it has to be with my awareness, my, you know, knowledge,
and I have basically, like I said, effectively ruled myself out because
I've indicated I want to buy the bread, not I want to
receive it. אמר רבי יהודה. amar Rabbi Yehuda. So now רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda says, and this is what we quoted earlier, במה דברים
אמורים בעירובי תחומין. bamei devarim amurim be'eiruvei techumin. When is it so
important to have this guy's buy-in, awareness? When it's עירוב תחומין, eiruv
techumin, when if you make עירוב eiruv in one direction you hurt
him in the other. אבל בעירובי חצירות מערבין לדעתו ושלא לדעתו. aval
be'eiruvei chatzeiros mearvin leda'ato veshela leda'ato. In עירובי חצירות eiruvei chatzeiros it
doesn't really matter, it's all
to his benefit. So presumably what he's saying is even in this
case where to some degree I've ruled myself out, I've signaled that
I want to buy it, not that I want to receive it,
says who cares whether you've signaled that? At the end of the
day, it's all to your benefit. And we're going to be קונה
koneh *koneh* it for you whether that was indicative of how you
acted when you gave the money to the baker or not. לפי
שזוכין לאדם שלא בפניו *Lefi shezochin l'adam shelo befanav*, you can benefit
somebody not in their presence even without their awareness. ואין חבין לאדם
אלא Ela, שלא בפניו *V'ein chavin l'adam ela shelo befanav*, but you
cannot injure them and you would injure them by עירובי תחומין *eruvei
techumin* because you'd make them lose on one side what they would
gain on the other. Okay, so this is the רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda *Rebbe Yehuda* we quoted before that basically says that you can
go ahead whatever I've indicated, you can go ahead and make me
a part of your עירוב eiruv. *eruv*, especially if you're using your
food, not my food, because it's only a benefit to me. So
that's how the גמרא *Gemara* tries to save this.
This is supposed to be like, you know, this nice thing about
איבה *eivah*, so I'd give a little bit...
well, that's true. Well, sometimes we have to beat people into, to
get rid of the איבה *eivah*. So anyway, מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר
*Mai ta'ama d'Rebbe Eliezer*? What is the reasoning of רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer, *Rebbe Eliezer* that says that the money makes me a partner
in the bread? הלא משך *Halo mashach*? I didn't actually do משיכה
meshikha *meshichah*. I didn't take physical possession of the bread. So אמר
רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה *Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar
Avuha*, עשאן רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer כארבעה פרקים בשנה *Asaun Rebbe Eliezer
k'arba'ah perakim bashanah*. He made it like those four times of the
year where even if you just give money, you become an owner
even without taking possession. What are the four times of the year?
By specific things. דתנן *Detnan*, we taught in the משנה Mishna *Mishnah*
in חולין *Chullin*, בארבעה פרקים אלו משחיטין את הטבח על כרחו *B'arba'ah
perakim elu mashchitin es hatabach al karcho*. In these four times of
the year, you can make the butcher slaughter the animal even if
he doesn't want to. What does that mean? The following case. אפילו
שור שוה אלף דינר *Afilu shor shoveh elef dinar*. You have an
ox that's worth a thousand dollars. ואין לוקח אלא דינר *V'ein lokeach
ela dinar*. And the guy that came to the butcher bought a
dollar's worth of meat. Okay, and he bought it presumably in the,
that cow itself. Okay, so you, he owns a dollar of meat
and the only way you're going to get a dollar of meat
is שחטינג *shechting* your cow. You have no choice. You have to
give him what he bought. He bought the dollar of meat. So
you שחט shecht *shecht* a cow. וכופין אותו
לשחוט *V'kofin oso lishchot*. You force him to שחט *shecht*. And what
are these four times of the year? Part of the reason we're
saying all this, which the גמרא *Gemara* will say, is because it's
time for everybody's having a nice סעודת יום טוב Yom Tov, *seudas
Yom Tov* and a nice meal, and therefore we want to ensure
that people that are out there to buy their meat get, get
the meat that they want to buy, even here at the sort
of cost of the butcher. So what are the four times? ערב
יום כיפור *Erev Yom Kippur*... if you look at רש"י Rashi *Rashi*,
רש"י *Rashi* says בארבעה פרקים אלו *b'arba'ah perakim elu*, right? He says
ערב יום טוב Yom Tov הראשון של פסח *Erev Yom Tov harishon
shel Pesach*, obviously for the, for the סדר *Seder*, you know, and
eating with the קרבן פסח *korban Pesach*. ערב יום טוב של עצרת
*Erev Yom Tov shel Atzeres*, ערב יום טוב של שבועות *Erev Yom
Tov shel Shavuos*. ערב ראש השנה *Erev Rosh Hashanah*, ערב ראש השנה
*Erev Rosh Hashanah*, which is also a יום טוב *Yom Tov*, obviously.
וערב יום טוב האחרון של חג *V'erev Yom Tov ha'achron shel chag*,
and the last day of
שמיני עצרת *Shemini Atzeres*. Now what happened to first day of סוכות
*Succos*? So תוספות Tosfos *Tosafos* quotes I think ירושלמי *Yerushalmi* whatever that
says people are too busy putting up their סוכה *succah*, getting the
לולב *lulav* and אתרוג *esrog* ready, so they don't have as big
of a meal on the first day of סוכות *Succos*. And ערב
יום הכיפורים בגליל *Erev Yom HaKippurim baGalil*, since there's a מצוה *mitzvah*
to eat on ערב יום כיפור *Erev Yom Kippur*, right? In גליל
*Galil* they really made it like a type of a סעודת יום
טוב *seudas Yom Tov*. Well, the question is, it's a מצוה *mitzvah*
to eat, whether you make it into like a סעודת יום טוב
*seudas Yom Tov* is a different discussion. Okay, so anyway, those are
the four times that the person, if even if he just gave
his dollar, he's an owner of the, in the meat, and you
and therefore the only way to provide it is by שחטינג *shechting*
the cow. You have to do that. So the גמרא *Gemara* says,
now the גמרא *Gemara* asks about the mechanism of this. We might
understand the motivation, but what's the mechanism? So the גמרא *Gemara*... oh,
first it says לפיכך אם מת, מת ללוקח *Lefichach im meis, meis
lalokeach*. And therefore if the cow dies, then the purchaser is out,
because the money, when he gave the money, he already became an
owner. So you're now an owner in one one-thousandth of the cow.
If the cow is dead, you can't ask for other meat, you
already bought that meat, and therefore, you know, you get, you have
the נבלה *neveilah* meat, but you but you're stuck. So basically the
point being that as soon as he paid the money, he became
an owner. And therefore I can force you to give me the
meat, but if something happens to it, I lose out. Now, the
גמרא *Gemara* says, והלא משך *V'halo mashach*? Now how does that work?
You didn't do משיכה meshikha. *meshichah*. So אמר רב הונא *Amar Rav
Huna*, בשמשך *Beshemaschach*. No, we mean you did משיכה meshikha, *meshichah*. So
first of all, then what's the whole point, what's the חידוש *chiddush*
of all any of this? And the גמרא *Gemara* says אי הכי
*ei hachi*, if that's true that all this is you actually took
possession, like maybe you took the whole cow to, you know, to
take possession of the one one-thousandth that you owned, אימא סיפא *eima
seifa*, let's look at the end of this משנה *Mishnah*. בשאר ימות
השנה אינו כן *Beshear yemot hashanah eino kein*. During the rest of
the year, this doesn't work this way. ולפיכך אם מת, מת למוכר
*Ulefichach im meis, meis lamocher*. When it dies, you have you don't
yet even after you've paid for it, you don't yet own the
meat and it's the owner's loss. You can't force the owner to
שחט *shecht* it. The owner can, the owner can, can give you
your money back. The sale hasn't finalized yet. But because it hasn't
finalized, then if it if it dies, it's the owner's loss. So
it's very clear that the difference is that in the first case,
as soon as you paid the money, you took possession right away.
And therefore you can force him to give you the meat even
if he has to שחט *shecht* the cow, but it's your meat
so if something happens it's your loss. And then in the second
case, you haven't taken possession yet and therefore it's his loss but
you also can't force him. He can give you the money back.
So what's the difference? So why in one case does it work
one case it doesn't based on what time of year it is?
So אמאי amai. המשיכה and if you said you did משיכה meshikha
then say it in both cases so אמאי. אמר רב שמואל בר
יצחק לעולם בשלא משך. Amar Rav Shmuel bar Yitzchak le'olam beshelo mashakh.
You're right. Obviously the first case is you didn't do משיכה. הכא
במאי עסקינן בשזיכה לו על ידי אחר. hakha bemai askinan bishezikha lo
al yedei akher.
So what happened though? The mechanism that it works is, you gave
me the dollar to buy a pound of meat, whatever, ten dollars
to buy a pound of meat, okay? And I didn't give you
the meat yet, but I went over to somebody else, the guy
who works for me, and I said here, take possession, or I
gave him the cow and said, take possession of one pound of
meat for Charlie here in this cow. Okay, so it worked by
doing it for somebody else, right, we've been talking about that, זיכה
על ידי אחר, zikha al yedei akher, a third party takes possession
for you. So still, why does that work during the four times
of the year and not during the rest of the year? So
the question is, is it to your benefit, you the purchaser, to
take possession as soon as you give the money? And that depends
on what time of year it is, because remember, somebody can do
it for your sake without your participation only if it's an
unadulterated benefit, only if it's a clear benefit. So the difference here
is not that the mechanism is that we give up the idea
for משיכה, we give up the act of the קנין. kinyan. That
is the mechanism, but the question is whether it's to your benefit
or not to have a third person do it. So let's take
a look.
הכא במאי עסקינן בשזיכה לו על ידי אחר. hakha bemai askinan bishezikha
lo al yedei akher. ובארבע פרקים אלו, u-ve-arba prakim elu, these four
times of the year, דזכות הוא לו, de-zkhut hu lo, that it's
a benefit for you to have possession of this meat, because we
would say look, everybody is eating meat, it's
יום טוב, so what's the downside of not having possession is that
the butcher could back out. I'm not going to שחט the whole
cow for you. Okay, that's the downside- the- so I'm sorry, let
me say, the upside of having possession right away, let me say
that. The upside of having possession right away is that the owner
can't back out. The downside of having possession right away is you
might want to back out. The animal might die. So in a
normal time of the year, those are pretty evenly weighted, and who
knows, maybe you want to have a cheaper dinner, you don't want
to have meat for dinner, you want to have your options more
open. So in a normal time of the year, you don't want
to have to own it, have closed off your options until you
actually take possession. But these four times of the year, everybody is
eating meat, and therefore it's clearly to your benefit that you should
own it as sooner rather than later so that the butcher doesn't
have the possibility of backing out. And that's the difference. ובארבע פרקים
אלו, u-ve-arba prakim elu, דזכות הוא לו, de-zkhut hu lo,
it's an unequivocal benefit to take possession right away, because you're not
going to want to back out, and you want to lock him
in. זכין לו שלא בפניו, zakhin lo shelo befanav, then somebody else
can take possession even not in your presence. ובשאר ימות השנה, u-vish'ar
yemot hashanah, the rest of the year, that you might want to
back out, you might not want to have meat, דחובה הוא לו,
de-chovah hu lo, that you lose something by having your options limited,
אין חבין לו אלא בפניו, ein chavin lo ela befanav, then that
can only be with your participation. So the first answer is the
way it works is through a third party. ורב אילא אמר רבי
יוחנן, ve-Rav Ila amar Rabbi Yochanan,
and this is how it ties back to our משנה: בארבע פרקים
אלו העמידו חכמים דבריהם על דברי תורה. be-arba prakim elu he'emidu chakhamim
divreihem al divrei Torah.
These four times of the year, forget you used a third party.
These four times of the year they said we would go by
the biblical rule. The biblical rule is, is that money is what
effects the transaction. רבנן, rabanan, you have to take possession of the
object, you have to do משיכה or הגבהה. hagbahah. But biblically, the
money itself effects the transaction. So therefore, again, coming from the perspective
that it's to your benefit that you should take possession right away
in the case of the butcher, so we're saying the way it
works is not that the butcher has to give it to a
third party, he might not agree or whatever, we want to actually
empower you that the deal is sealed as quickly as possible. So
we say as soon as you pay the money the transaction is
binding, going back to the biblical rule. And the same way that's
true here in these four
times, says רבי אליעזר, I'll say the same by עירוב. eiruv Because
I want you to be able to carry in your courtyard on
שבת, Shabbat, so therefore even if you paid money and it sort
of is trading problems, I'm going to make it for this time
that the money actually effects the transaction. The same way we say
it for those four times, I'm going to say it here to
allow you to make the עירוב eruv work and that you can
carry in your courtyard. Now let's see why that was- why they
did that. דאמר רבי יוחנן, de-amar Rabbi Yochanan, דבר תורה מעות קונות,
devar Torah ma'ot konot, biblically money effects the transaction. מפני מה אמרו
משיכה קונה, mipnei mah amru meshikha konah,
why did they say you have to draw the object to you,
you have to take possession of the goods? גזירה שמא יאמר לו
נשרפו חטיך בעלייה, gezeirah shema yomar lo nisrepu chitakha ba'aliyah, because what's
going to happen? You're going to give me a hundred dollars for
my cow, or for wheat, and then you come a week later
to take possession of the goods, and the deal's already final if
we go by money, you are now the owner, and I say,
terrible thing happened last week, fire broke out, the cow died, I'm
sorry, obviously the point is if I'm totally
made. but it might actually be there was a fire, but I'm
not gonna try so hard to save your product if it's still
your product. So basically the rabbis said if it's already your product
then you can't back out. So the rabbis actually said, therefore to
protect your interests of the purchaser, the deal is not final until
actually you take possession of the object itself. You don't want him
to be holding onto your object and not be highly motivated to
protect it from damage. Okay, now תוספות Tosfos asks the question, I
don't get it. Why don't we say the same thing? I've given
you the money, okay, now the deal isn't binding, so I'm gonna
come back and say give me my money back, okay, and you'll
say, oh you know what? Your money got lost, right? It's still
I'm still holding onto an object that's yours before, right? So you
know, so why is that any different? So תוספות basically says because
money demands a higher level of care. There's a whole discussion in
בבא מציעא Bava Metzia about the חיוב chiyuv of שומרים. shomrim. You're
a שומר shomer on my object. If my object was a normal
thing like wheat, your level of care is low. So therefore, you
could actually get, you know, wouldn't take as much pains to protect
it. But in the case where now I've given you the money
and the deal isn't final and you're holding onto my money, the
level of care is much higher when it actually comes to money,
and therefore my interests are more protected. So by getting rid of
the biblical
transaction and replacing it with this idea of taking possession of the
objects, we are protecting the interests of the of the purchaser. Now
רש"י says how do you know that biblically מעות קונות? moas konos?
So he quotes a פסוק pasuk by הקדש Hekdesh where you use
money. But that's a question how does that פסוק pasuk indicate all
types of transactions. So תוספות is a nice little תוספות דבר תורה
devar Torah מעות קונות moas konos not so little, but anyway, if
you look at the end תוספות makes this nice point in terms
of the פסוקים. psukim. He says ועוד מפרשי דהיינו טעמא דמעות קונות
דבר תורה ve'od meforashei de'hainu ta'ama de'moas konos devar Torah about eight
lines before the bottom of this תוספות דבר תורה. devar Torah. He
says ועוד מפרשי דהיינו טעמא דמעות קונות דבר תורה דסתם קניין דקרא
בכסף ביארי. ve'od meforashei de'hainu ta'ama de'moas konos devar Torah de'stam kinyan
de'kra bekesef bairi. That's
with the simple sense of all the פסוקים psukim is that money
affects the affects the transaction. כדתנן בכמה דוכתי קניין מכסף Ki'de'asnan be'kama
duchte kinyan mikesef אכלה בכסף תשברני ocha bekesef tishbareni sell me food
with money שדות בכסף יקנו sados bekesef yiknu so you know ואף
על גב דספר מקנה ve'af al gav de'sefer mikne etc. etc.
Anyway he says right, so עפרון Efron אכילה achilai by אברהם Avraham
although right.
So anyway he says he says all of all around it sounds
like you give money that takes that takes effect simple sense of
the פסוקים. psukim. So anyway but it's quite fascinating you know because
here you have that the rabbis basically you know took this institution
it wasn't like a מצווה. It was like a detail in you
know in how transactions take place and say that this actually is
counterproductive to you know the societal interests and they overrode it with
this rabbinic way of taking possession which is משיכה ולא מעות. meshicha
v'lo moas. There's an interesting debate of the ראשונים rishonim which is
is it that if I give you money and I haven't taken
possession of the object is it that I don't own it at
all or is it that I own it but I'm allowed to
back out? Okay because the גמרא actually says that if I give
you the money and I haven't taken possession and then I back
out I get a curse which basically is מי שפרע Mi sheparah
the one who you know the one who paid back the דור
המבול dor hamabul and the דור הפלגה dor haflaga will pay back
somebody who doesn't see through his promises. Okay but the question is
it's a very fascinating idea normally in הלכה halacha we don't have
like you can do it but you get a curse. And according
to some ראשונים rishonim the idea behind that is is that it
still what I did still biblically owned it but the rabbis gave
me the right to negate the transaction. Okay so it's an interesting
way did they completely remove the biblical institution that money takes possession
or did they give me the right to negate it? But anyway
because but the point being that that is biblically how it works
so in these four times of the year where we want to
make sure that everybody has meat for יום טוב or when according
to רבי אליעזר when we want to make sure that you're able
to make your עירוב eruv. we will allow ourselves to revert to
the biblical model and to say that the money actually is what
took effect.
By קידושין kiddushin once you give the money that's it right you
can't back out right.
But קידושין kiddushin is not there are some things that still as
כסף kesef right. It's by it's by chattel it's by you know
movable objects that they overrode it. Real estate not קידושין kiddushin not
etc. right. Okay so let's take a look now ומודים בשאר כל
אדם. u'modim bish'ar kol adam. Now that's if I gave my money
to the butcher or to the storekeeper that then I'm trying to
actually buy the object. But if I just gave money to a
סתם person then I'm just asking him to be you know do
something for me to take to be a שליח shaliach in taking
in taking the food for the עירוב. eruv So מאן שאר כל
אדם man sh'ar kol adam who's everybody else? אמר רב בעל הבית
balabayas meaning a normal homeowner וכן אמר שמואל ve'chen amar Shmuel בעל
הבית balabayas גמר שמואל gemar Shmuel לא שנו אלא נחתום lo shanu
ela nachton that's only a baker אבל בעל הבית קונה aval balabayas
koneh it works by the בעל הבית balabayas now קונה is a
funny word because again רש"י says it's not really that it works
but it's really that but it's really that
that if I give it to a normal person then by giving
them the money it means when they they you know when they
go to collect the עירוב eruv you should be מזכה mezakeh the
עירוב eruv for me. I'm making him a שליח shaliach I'm not
purchasing an object. ואמר שמואל V’amar Shmuel and שמואל also says לא
שנו אלא מעה. lo shanu ela ma’ah. When is this a problem
that giving the money to the baker doesn’t work? If you give
money. אבל כלי קונה, Aval kli koneh, if you give an object
it does work. Why? Because then it’s no longer קנין כסף. kinyan
kesef. What קנין kinyan is it? Anybody guess? We just had it
in מגילת רות, Megillas Rus, קנין חליפין. kinyan chalipin. Okay, so if
it’s not money but it’s a כלי, kli, then I actually do
take
possession. ואמר שמואל V’amar Shmuel לא שנו אלא דאמר לו זכי לי.
lo shanu ela d’amar lo zechei li. אבל אמר לו Aval amar
lo ערב לי, arev li, if I said to the butcher, 'take
possession of me for this with this dollar,' it doesn't work. I
should own it with this dollar. But if I said, 'make an
עירוב eruv, for me,' that’s like giving it to the non-butcher, and
שליח שוויה וקני. shaliach shavya v’kanei. I made him a שליח. shaliach.
Okay, and it works. אמר רב יהודה Amar Rav Yehuda and רב
יהודה Rav Yehuda says all of this thing that I gave the
money and therefore technically I wanted to buy it and I didn't
want to receive it, that there, and therefore it’s a problem, he
says that’s all
by
עירוב תחומין. eruv techumin. But by עירוב חצרות, eruv chatzeiros, go ahead
and do it for me. What do I care? אמר רב יהודה
אמר שמואל. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel. Yes, why needs...
how is עירוב תחומין eruv techumin a חובה? chovah?
I’ve been saying that because whatever you gain on one side you
lose on the other. So therefore you need my full participation. Okay.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי יהודה. Amar Rav Yehuda amar
Shmuel halacha k’Rabbi Yehuda. We rule like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that
says that we have more latitude by עירובי חצרות eruvei chatzeiros because
it’s always to my benefit. ולא עוד, V’lo od, not only that,
אלא כל מקום ששנה רבי יהודה בעירובין הלכה כמותו. ela kol makom
sheshana Rabbi Yehuda b’Eruvin halacha k’moso. Wherever he says anything by עירובין
Eruvin we rule like
him. אמר ליה רב חנה בר קטינא לרב יהודה: Amar leh Rav
Chana bar Katina l’Rav Yehuda: אמר שמואל אפילו במבוי שנטלו קורותיו ולחיו?
afilu b’mavoi she’nitlu korosov v’lechayav? We are going to see later that
if a מבוי, mavoi, the beam or the post fell down on
שבת, Shabbos, that according to... according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda it’s
okay since it was okay when שבת Shabbos began even if the
beam or the... or the post fell down. So he said, 'would
you say that we also rule like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda, because
you say we always rule like him by עירובין?' Eruvin? אמר ליה:
Amar leh: בעירובין אמרתי לך B'eruvin amarti lach ולא במחיצה. v’lo b’mechitza.
No, that although that’s part of what lets you carry, we’ve seen
this distinction before, that’s about making your full complement of walls. That
is a different halachic category than the idea of joining together in
the loaf of bread. So when I said we rule like him
by עירובין, Eruvin, it means that you have your walls and now
all of the houses or all the courtyards are coming together. But
in the issues of the walls themselves we don’t necessarily rule like
him. אמר ליה רב אחא בריה דרבא לרב אשי, Amar leh Rav
Acha brei d’Rava l’Rav Ashi, הלכה, halacha, we rule like רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda מכלל דפליגי. m’klal d’pligi. It sounds like he’s arguing, but
that there’s an argument. But who argues on the idea that we’re
more lenient that by עירוב תחומין—excuse eruv techumin me, עירוב חצרות eruv
chatzeiros it’s a benefit and you could do it שלא מדעתו? she’lo
m’da’ato? והאמר רבי יהושע בן לוי, V’ha’amar Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi, not
only that, רבי יהושע בן לוי Rabbi Yehoshua ben Levi said כל
מקום שאמר רבי יהודה אימתי ובמה במשנתנו, kol makom she’amar Rabbi Yehuda
eimasi u’vameh b’mishnasenu, anytime רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda uses the phrase in
a משנה, 'when do they say this?' or 'in what circumstances?', אימתי
ובמה, eimasi u’vameh, אינו אלא לפרש דברי חכמים. eino ela l’faresh divrei
Chachamim. He’s not coming to disagree, he’s coming to explain to, you
know, to qualify what the rabbis say but in an expository way,
not to have a different opinion. So therefore I don’t think that
anybody argues it. So the גמרא says, and this just is a
nice closure from what we began today, ולא פליגי? V’lo pligi? How
can you say they don’t argue? והא תנן: V’ha tnan: ניתוספו עליהם
מוסיף ומזכה וצריך להודיע. nitosfu aleihem mosif u’mezakeh v’tzarich l’hodia. When there
are new members you can be מזכה mezakeh them, take the food
for them for the עירוב, eruv but you have to let them
know. Right? Why do you have to let them know? It’s only
to their benefit. So right? We said this before. Is this an
idea that you have to, that even by עירוב תחומין eruv techumin
you have to let the person know? So you see there's a
debate. גמרא says, no, that not necessarily is a... that's not necessarily
a different opinion. התם בחצר שבין שני מבואות. Hasam b’chatzer she’bein sheni
mevo’os. Like we said before when we began today but we rejected
the possibility, here the גמרא saying maybe רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. would
agree with that case. That case is that the חצר chatzer could
have joined either מבוי. mavoi. And therefore it’s not clearly to their
benefit. But when it’s clearly to their benefit, who cares about whether
the person knows? Who cares what he tried to buy, what he
tried to do? Maybe everybody would say you could do it because
it’s to the benefit. So let’s just read one more line. והאמר
רב שיזבי אמר רב חסדא: V’ha’amar Rav Shizbi amar Rav Chisda: זאת
אומרת חלוקין עליו חבריו על רבי יהודה. Zos omeres chalukin alav chavrav
al Rabbi Yehuda. But we just started today’s דף, daf, says the
גמרא, by saying a position that no, that the previous משנה argues
on רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda So you see it is debated whether
we always, everybody agrees to רבי יהודה’s Rabbi Yehuda idea that you
can always do it without the person's participation and awareness. אלא, the
גמרא says: גברא אגברא קרמית? gavra a’gavra karmis? What are you doing,
you know, trying to show a contradiction of one אמורא Amora with
another? מר סבר פליגי ומר סבר לא פליגי. Mar savar pligi u’mar
savar lo pligi. Good. So there’s those that say that when רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda. says במה bameh he's only explaining. So according to
that, nobody disagrees with רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda Everybody agrees you can
do an עירוב without making the participants aware, an עירוב חצרות. eruv
chatzeiros. And the other opinion is no, there's a debate. There's a
debate and one position said even you have to make them aware.
רבי יהודה says you don't have to make them aware. But according
to both positions... we say we rule like ר' יהודה, Reb Yehuda,
meaning either everybody says ר' יהודה, Reb Yehuda, there's no debate, or
there is a debate and we rule like ר' יהודה. Reb Yehuda.
But either way, ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda says by עירוב חצרות eruv
chatzeros where it's only to the person's benefit, you can go ahead
and do it for them, even they were trying to do something
else, they were trying to buy and instead you're going to give
it to them freely or whatever they were trying to do, you
can go ahead and do it for them, especially if you're using
your food and not their food because it's only to their benefit.
Okay, and now we are caught up.